<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the sulphur-bath at Knarsbrough in York-shire By Will. Simpson, M.D.</title>
            <author>Simpson, William, M.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832785</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60264)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2060:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the sulphur-bath at Knarsbrough in York-shire By Will. Simpson, M.D.</title>
                  <author>Simpson, William, M.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Will. Cooper at the Pellican in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  Knaresborough --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sulphurous water --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37259:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE Sulphur-Bath AT <hi>KNARSBROUGH</hi> IN YORK-SHIRE.</p>
            <p>BY WILL. SIMPSON, <hi>M. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Cooper</hi> at the <hi>Pellican</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:37259:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37259:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of the <hi>Sulphur-Bath</hi> at <hi>Knarsbrough,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning its Cauſes and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</head>
            <p>THat I may not be injurious to what I have already writ in my two former Books, entituled <hi>Hydrologia Chymica</hi> and <hi>Hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Eſſays,</hi> concerning the <hi>Sulphur-Well</hi> at <hi>Knarsbrough,</hi> as a <hi>mineral wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of great uſe in its virtues inwardly taken. But now deſigning an account thereof, as a <hi>Bath</hi> for outward uſe, ſhall therefore, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the better underſtanding of what I aim at, here reſume ſo much of my former <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> concerning the <hi>Eſsential ingredients,</hi> and <hi>neceſsary principles</hi> of that <hi>Water;</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an addition of ſome more recent <hi>obſervations,</hi> as may ſerve to illuſtrate what I now intend to be my preſent task: Our method will be as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37259:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. To lay down the conſtitutive ingredients or <hi>mineral principles</hi> of that <hi>Water.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. To ſhew the proceſs (as near as we can apprehend) <hi>Nature</hi> uſeth in the preparing this <hi>excellent water.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. To ſhew the difference betwixt this and other natural <hi>Hot-Baths,</hi> as in their original and inbred <hi>principles;</hi> ſo alſo in ſome ſort as to their virtues.</item>
               <item>4. To ſhew how, and by what means, the <hi>Sulphur</hi> (as the chief <hi>mineral ingredient</hi> in this water) is ſo opened, as to become, not only ſo ſubtile, as thence to be ſolvable <hi>odore tenus</hi> therein; but alſo ſo <hi>volatile,</hi> as to paſs off in a continual <hi>ſteame,</hi> and inſenſible <hi>effluvium.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. How this <hi>Sulphur-water</hi> comes not much ſhort, as to its <hi>original principles,</hi> nor is much (if at all) inferiour in its efficacy, to ſome other <hi>Sulphur-waters,</hi> which are <hi>Hot-Baths;</hi> inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as this is lately found to be <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> for <hi>outward applications,</hi> as well as thoſe by late <hi>obſervation</hi> are remark'd for inward uſe.</item>
               <item>6. To ſhew, that the artificial heating of the <hi>Sulphur-water,</hi> bears ſome analogy to the <hi>inbred heat</hi> of other <hi>Baths,</hi> as they come hot out of the Earth.</item>
               <item>7. To ſhew, how <hi>Art</hi> may imitate <hi>Nature,</hi> (but yet from the ſame <hi>principles</hi>) in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of moſt <hi>Baths, viz.</hi> how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſuch <hi>Baths</hi> artificially, as are natural.</item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37259:3"/>
               <item>Laſtly, To inquire how and after what manner this <hi>Sulphur-water</hi> performs thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected helps, as a <hi>Bath:</hi> where, in ſhort, will be <hi>illuſtrated</hi> its various virtues in order to the help of ſeveral <hi>Maladies.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, As to the conſtituent ingredients or <hi>mineral principles</hi> of this <hi>water:</hi> We ſay they are compriz'd in theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. A <hi>marine</hi> or <hi>foſſil Salt.</hi> 2. A <hi>Sulphurous Apporrhea</hi> or <hi>ſteam</hi> of <hi>Sulphur.</hi> Laſtly, A little <hi>aluminous acidity.</hi> As to the firſt, viz. <hi>Salt,</hi> is apparent both from its brackiſh taſte, as alſo from what <hi>remains</hi> upon its <hi>distillation</hi> or <hi>evaporation;</hi> of which we find betwixt one and two drams in a quart thereof: as we further ſhew in our <hi>Hydrologia Chymica,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the <hi>Sulphrous principle,</hi> thats ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, 1. From its Taſte and Smell; as alſo from its hogo upon the <hi>riflings</hi> and <hi>regurgitations</hi> of the Stomack, after taking thereof. 2. From its colouring of <hi>Silver</hi> dipt therein; which it doth as readily as the ſolution or waſhings of <hi>crocus metallorum</hi> from the <hi>Sulphur</hi> of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony;</hi> or as the ſolution of <hi>common Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> in the preparing <hi>Lac Sulphuris,</hi> both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made from the <hi>Acids</hi> of <hi>alcalizate Salts,</hi> as will appear (although a paradox) more clearly anon.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, from its <hi>colouring</hi> of <hi>Silver</hi> by its very <hi>Steams,</hi> as we ſhall ſhew more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37259:4"/>
            <p>Now the queſtion may be ask'd, whence this <hi>mineral water</hi> has its <hi>Sulphur?</hi> I anſwer, that there are plenty of <hi>vitriolin Marcaſites</hi> well ſaturate with <hi>Sulphur,</hi> out of which I have, by an artifice (taught in my <hi>Hydrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Eſsays</hi>) ſeparated perfect <hi>Brimstone,</hi> which melted into <hi>magdalions</hi> or <hi>rolls,</hi> are not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable any manner of way from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: beſides which <hi>Marcaſites</hi> (found not far off this Spring) the very adjacent <hi>Earth</hi> is full of <hi>Brimſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, As to the ingredient of <hi>Alom,</hi> its diſcoverable theſe ways following, firſt from the <hi>Alom-Bed</hi> through which this <hi>water</hi> at laſt paſſeth, or at leaſt toucheth upon, as is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to any eye that will look at it, being cloſe adjoyning to the <hi>exit</hi> of the <hi>water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By its <hi>acidity</hi> in the <hi>water,</hi> as is evident from its <hi>curdling</hi> of <hi>Milk:</hi> for the <hi>Salt</hi> ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the <hi>Sulphur-water,</hi> being put into boyling <hi>Milk,</hi> will make it ſhil into <hi>Curds</hi> and <hi>Whey,</hi> as if ſome <hi>acidum</hi> was poured thereto, which <hi>common Salt</hi> will not do; for we try'd both, and that in the ſame proportion, and found the <hi>Sulphur Salt</hi> to cauſe a ſpeedy <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> and that in great quantity; and the common Salt made a little <hi>ſeparation,</hi> of a <hi>lighter coagulum,</hi> but did not make it ſhil, or alter the ſeeming colour or conſiſtence of the <hi>Milk:</hi> And laſtly, if the powder of <hi>Coral</hi> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37259:4"/>
               <hi>Crabs-Eyes</hi> be put thereto, they imbibe or mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the <hi>acidity</hi> of the <hi>Alom,</hi> and cauſe a <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kieneſs</hi> from the <hi>volatile Sulphur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the three aforeſaid ingredients are found to be the <hi>constitutive principles</hi> of this <hi>water,</hi> ſo that neither <hi>vitriol</hi> nor <hi>nitre</hi> (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome imagine the contrary) are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd therein, is evident, firſt as to <hi>vitriol</hi> (which gives the moſt ſuſpition from the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its <hi>Marcaſites,</hi> found not far from the <hi>Well</hi>) becauſe it will ſtrike no <hi>tincture</hi> with <hi>Galls,</hi> as we ſhall ſhortly further evince: And as to <hi>Nitre,</hi> there is not the leaſt ſuſpition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from what is <hi>ſeparable</hi> from the <hi>water,</hi> nor from any <hi>mineral glebe</hi> adjacent thereto, that we have yet diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to the proceſs <hi>Nature</hi> uſeth in the preparing this excellent <hi>mineral water,</hi> or the manner of her mixing the foreſaid ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients, by her <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> in the bowels of the <hi>Earth,</hi> in order to the making up the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Sulphur-Bath:</hi> In ſhort has, a <hi>water Spring,</hi> ſuppoſe, paſſing through or by a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera</hi> of <hi>foſſil Salt,</hi> part of which it diſſolves, and afterwards in its current either <hi>meeting</hi> with ſome <hi>acid juice,</hi> whether of <hi>vitriol</hi> or of other <hi>mineral glebes,</hi> becomes impregnate therewith, and obviating, or rather ſuperve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a <hi>Sulphurous Mineral,</hi> from the concourſe of which two, happens a <hi>Fermentation:</hi> or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37259:5"/>elſe, this Saline Solution comes upon a <hi>minera,</hi> whether that of <hi>vitriol,</hi> or what other ſoever it be, in the <hi>meanders</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> whoſe <hi>principles</hi> are yet <hi>crude,</hi> and onely <hi>embriona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivs;</hi> whereupon it ſets thoſe native and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genit <hi>principles</hi> awork, into a <hi>Fermentation,</hi> either way, I ſay, it becomes capable of rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that inteſtine motion, we call <hi>Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and thence of ſo ſubtilizing and volati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the <hi>Sulphur,</hi> as to make it ſolvable in <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> (as we have illuſtrated more demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly above in our <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Hot-Baths.</hi>) But not ſtaying here, becauſe of the continual afflux and preſſure of <hi>water,</hi> at length it paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth through an <hi>Alom-bed,</hi> whoſe <hi>acidity</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitates in great part the body of the <hi>diſſolv'd Sulphur;</hi> in which very <hi>precipitation</hi> happens its fatid ſmell, and <hi>Sulphurous hogo,</hi> which onely paſſing through a ſlender <hi>Colander</hi> of Sand, retains its lately contracted odour; where it filters off from the more <hi>groſs</hi> preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated <hi>body,</hi> and ſo makes its <hi>exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which gives great probability of <hi>heat</hi> in the ſource of its <hi>original mixture,</hi> and that if the <hi>Spring</hi> did immediately after that <hi>Solution</hi> and <hi>Fermentation</hi> break forth, it would be <hi>hot,</hi> at leaſt <hi>warm,</hi> after the manner of other <hi>Hot-Baths;</hi> but being carryed on in a longer line, in its <hi>ſubterraneal current,</hi> before it breaks forth, <hi>looſeth</hi> that <hi>heat</hi> contiacted upon the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37259:5"/>
               <hi>Fermentation</hi> of the aforeſaid <hi>mineral juices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is likewiſe remarkable concerning <hi>Alom intereſted</hi> in the fabrick of this <hi>water, viz.</hi> that I have (as often as I pleas'd to make the experiment) taken ſome of the <hi>ſucculent Alom</hi> ſlate or ſtone (found cloſe by the <hi>Well</hi>) which has had the <hi>Salt</hi> diſcernably extraver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which when I <hi>ſcrap'd</hi> into ſimple <hi>water,</hi> would with <hi>Galls</hi> forthwith <hi>ſtrike</hi> a deep <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> after the manner which the ſucculent <hi>Alom-ſtone</hi> doth, which is got upon the <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough Bank,</hi> near that <hi>Spaw</hi> [about which our great controverſie, concerning that <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> being <hi>aluminous,</hi> and not <hi>vitriolin,</hi> did chiefly depend] which experiment I have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times ſhewed to <hi>perſons</hi> no leſs <hi>ingenious</hi> then <hi>inquiſitive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alſo order'd an infuſion to be made of ſome of the ſame <hi>Alom-ſtones</hi> in above a Gallon of <hi>freſh water,</hi> then to be <hi>evaporated</hi> to about half a Pint, which filtred, I evaporated fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Balneo M.</hi> to try if it would ſhoot <hi>per ſe,</hi> but it would not, onely came to a ſoft ſort of <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>mellago.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the third thing propounded, <hi>viz.</hi> the difference betwixt this and other natural <hi>Hot-Baths</hi> in their <hi>original principles,</hi> and <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary cauſes:</hi> We think that from what has already been ſaid, and eſpecially what yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be diſcours'd of, in the next, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37259:6"/>other <hi>ſucceeding propoſals,</hi> that the difference of theſe from other <hi>Sulphurous waters,</hi> both as to their <hi>origin</hi> and <hi>virtues,</hi> will ſufficiently be declared: And that <hi>Sulphur</hi> (of one ſort or other) is <hi>chiefly concern'd</hi> in the fabrick of all <hi>Hot-Baths,</hi> and other <hi>Sulphurous waters,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating with other <hi>concurring juices,</hi> the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them both.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As to the fourth propoſal, <hi>viz.</hi> how, and by what means, the <hi>Sulphur</hi> (as the chief <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ingredient</hi> in this <hi>water</hi>) is ſo <hi>opened,</hi> as to become, not onely ſo <hi>ſubtile,</hi> as thence to be ſolvable <hi>odore tenus,</hi> but alſo ſo <hi>volatile,</hi> as to paſs off in a <hi>continual ſteam,</hi> and <hi>inſenſible effluvium;</hi> For the great query is, how <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> may be ſo opened, as to make the <hi>Sulphur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> and other <hi>Sulphurous waters</hi> of the like nature.</p>
            <p>While I was therefore ſeriouſly ruminating upon this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> what it was that might truly be ſaid to <hi>open</hi> the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>crude Sulphur,</hi> whether it was an <hi>Acid</hi> or an <hi>Alcali,</hi> I began to conſider how many <hi>ways,</hi> and by what <hi>means,</hi> it was uſually ſo <hi>opened,</hi> as to make a <hi>ſolution</hi> in any <hi>Liquor:</hi> Firſt I conſidered it was <hi>ſolvable</hi> for the moſt part in all <hi>Oyles,</hi> by the help of <hi>Fire:</hi> and that I imagin'd happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the analogy of parts, betwixt <hi>Oyles</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs;</hi> both of them being chiefly <hi>Sulphurs</hi> under a <hi>diſguiſe,</hi> the one in a <hi>concrete,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37259:6"/>the other in a <hi>liquid form;</hi> both of them alſo in their <hi>bellies</hi> hiding their <hi>intrinſick Acids,</hi> the <hi>Oylie</hi> or <hi>Sulphurous parts</hi> of both by <hi>Fire</hi> melting together, in the <hi>fluid form</hi> of a <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> while the <hi>acidum,</hi> chiefly of the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,</hi> being thereby in part <hi>ſeparated,</hi> doth <hi>concreſcere</hi> into a <hi>ſaline form,</hi> under the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of <hi>cryſtals,</hi> as is obvious in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the <hi>Balſome</hi> of <hi>mineral Sulphur</hi> or <hi>Brimſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>vinous Spirits</hi> are <hi>vegetable Sulphurs,</hi> comminuted and ſubtiliz'd by <hi>Fermentation;</hi> ſo theſe are alſo <hi>ſuccedaneous</hi> to <hi>Oyles,</hi> in the ſolutions of <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> yet need previous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations by <hi>fixt Alcalies,</hi> (as they are called) for being ſo <hi>ſpiritualiz'd,</hi> are not ſuch apt <hi>menſtrua</hi> for ſolutions of <hi>crude Minerals,</hi> as <hi>Oyles</hi> are, although either of them are power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough for making very ſtrong and furious <hi>Fermentations</hi> with the aforeſaid <hi>mineral Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs,</hi> once by their <hi>congenial Acids,</hi> brought, by help of <hi>Fire,</hi> into a <hi>fluor,</hi> in the form of <hi>corroſive menſtrua:</hi> witneſs the high ebulliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons betwixt <hi>vinous Spirits</hi> or <hi>Oyles,</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Nitre, Aqua-fortis, Oyle</hi> of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> &amp;c. ſome of them ſo very furious in their <hi>Fermentation,</hi> as to ariſe to an <hi>actual flagration</hi> (as we elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where demonſtrate.)</p>
            <p>So that <hi>crude Sulphurs,</hi> unopened by the acuations of the <hi>acidum</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> (which alſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37259:7"/>ſharpen the implanted <hi>Acids</hi> of ſuch <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi>) do <hi>diſsolve</hi> quietly without any tumult, (if done leaſurely) and melt together into one <hi>Balſamick Liquor,</hi> (though if haſtily done with a pretty <hi>ſmart Fire,</hi> they make a <hi>crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling noiſe</hi>) whereas the foreſaid <hi>mineral Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs</hi> being <hi>ſubtiliz'd</hi> by their own <hi>Acids,</hi> fortified by the <hi>acidum</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> in their <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation,</hi> are brought thereby into a <hi>fluor</hi> of both <hi>principles,</hi> and if then mixed with the foreſaid <hi>vegetable Sulphurs,</hi> contract a furious <hi>Fermentation,</hi> from the freſh <hi>colliſions,</hi> betwixt <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> and if cloſe ſhut up, would break in pieces the ſtrongeſt Veſſels art could contrive.</p>
            <p>And as the foreſaid ſolutions of <hi>mineral Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs,</hi> are perform'd by <hi>Oyles</hi> and <hi>vinous Spirits,</hi> from analogy of parts; I conſidered whether other ſorts of ſolutions of <hi>crude Brimſtone,</hi> or the like <hi>Sulphurous Minerals,</hi> might not alſo be done, by the like analogy, and then I pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered upon the <hi>alterations</hi> made upon <hi>Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>fixt alcalies</hi> (which how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly call'd, we ſhew in our <hi>Halologia</hi>) and <hi>quick-lime,</hi> and by well weighing the matter, found, that as <hi>Brimſtone</hi> was diſſolvable in <hi>Oyle</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Wine,</hi> as aforeſaid, ſo <hi>fixt alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> work upon <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> no otherwiſe then as they are <hi>acido-ſulphurous Salts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37259:7"/>
            <p>For I conſidered that <hi>volatile Alcalies,</hi> ſuch as are all <hi>urinous Spirits,</hi> work not at all upon, nor cauſe any alteration in <hi>Sulphurs:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs follow, that wherein <hi>fixt</hi> and <hi>volatile alcalies</hi> do agree, or in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, which is common to them both, I mean, their <hi>precipitating faculty,</hi> neither of them is concern'd in the <hi>ſolutions</hi> of <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> and that is common, both to <hi>fixt</hi> and <hi>volatile Alcalies,</hi> to precipitate, what <hi>Acids</hi> have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd. Now the reaſon why <hi>urinous Spirits,</hi> I mean <hi>volatile Alcalies</hi> (as they are call'd) do not at all work upon <hi>Brimstone,</hi> is, becauſe they contain ſo very ſlender a texture of <hi>Acids,</hi> and no <hi>Sulphurs</hi> (if highly rectified) and therefore are incapable by analogy of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the aforeſaid <hi>bodies:</hi> how fixt <hi>Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> are a new <hi>compage</hi> of their own native <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> together with the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of <hi>urinous Spirits,</hi> (from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds its precipitating faculty) all bound up by the <hi>acidum</hi> of the <hi>Fire,</hi> (which is their <hi>vinculum</hi>) and not a <hi>ſimple Salt,</hi> we elſewhere in our <hi>History</hi> of <hi>Tartar,</hi> declare more at large.</p>
            <p>While I was pondering upon this matter, at length methought I eſpyed a great <hi>harmony</hi> in <hi>natures works;</hi> I ſaw that ſhe perform'd the ſame <hi>ſolutions</hi> of <hi>mineral Sulphurs,</hi> in ſome parts of the <hi>bowels</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> by her own <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrua</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37259:8"/>of <hi>Acids,</hi> prepared by her dextrous <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Chymistry</hi> (the very foundation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar of all we call <hi>Artificial</hi>) as ſhe did in other actions, reputed (amongſt moſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors) <hi>Heteroclites;</hi> and was the ſame in the latter, as the former; and from hence I ſaw, that reputed <hi>causticks,</hi> I mean <hi>fixt lixivial Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies,</hi> were no other then <hi>Acids,</hi> viz. of the <hi>Fire,</hi> fixt upon bodies: ſo that I found <hi>nature ſymbolical</hi> in all her <hi>actions,</hi> and always conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to her own <hi>principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I might <hi>improve</hi> this <hi>notion</hi> the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (not taken notice of by any other Author I know) I began to make a <hi>ſtrict ſcrutiny</hi> into the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>fixt Alcalies;</hi> I conſidered, Firſt, That the more <hi>Fire</hi> they endured, and the <hi>higher</hi> they were <hi>calcin'd,</hi> and the ſooner us'd after <hi>calcination,</hi> the <hi>ſtronger</hi> and more <hi>fiery Causticks</hi> they were.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they would never <hi>calcine</hi> to a ſtrong <hi>Salt,</hi> unleſs perform'd in <hi>open Veſſels</hi> or <hi>Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> where the <hi>Fire</hi> might more immediately touch upon them, and <hi>concentre</hi> its own <hi>acidum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That if after they were <hi>cold,</hi> and kept from the <hi>Air,</hi> and then <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Wine</hi> or <hi>Water</hi> was put thereto, thence a <hi>heat</hi> was preſently <hi>produc'd,</hi> which as I conceive, was from no other cauſe then this, <hi>viz.</hi> That either of thoſe <hi>Liquors,</hi> ſets the <hi>acidum,</hi> contracted from the <hi>Fire,</hi> and the <hi>Sulphur</hi> or <hi>volatile Alcaly</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37259:8"/>in the <hi>Salt,</hi> into a ſudden <hi>Fermentation,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving, and ſo putting them into an <hi>intestine colliſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And fourthly I conſidered, That the longer theſe <hi>Salts</hi> were expos'd to the <hi>Air,</hi> even to a ſolution <hi>per deliquium,</hi> the more mild and ſoft in operation they become; <hi>loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> thereby gradually their <hi>Acids</hi> imbibed from the <hi>Fire;</hi> inſomuch as by often ſolution <hi>per deliquium,</hi> the <hi>compage</hi> of that <hi>Salt,</hi> from the <hi>vinculum</hi> of the <hi>fiery Acid,</hi> is taken off, as that the whole may thence be <hi>reduc'd</hi> into an <hi>inſipid Water</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> (and no <hi>Arcauum</hi> neither.)</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That although theſe fixt <hi>lixivial Salts,</hi> do make ſtrong <hi>Ebullitions</hi> with <hi>Acids</hi> put to them, yet that happens, either betwixt the additional <hi>acid,</hi> and the <hi>Sulphur</hi> in the <hi>Salt,</hi> or betwixt it, and the <hi>volatile alcaly,</hi> bound up in the <hi>artificial concretion:</hi> That there are <hi>Sulphurs</hi> in thoſe <hi>Salts,</hi> or new textures of Plants, appears from their <hi>lixivial</hi> or <hi>ſaponary</hi> property: and that there are alſo <hi>volatile al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies,</hi> is evident from their precipitating fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and from their <hi>intestine ſtrugling</hi> with <hi>acids.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which may be added this <hi>obſervation,</hi> that after <hi>fixt alcalies</hi> have loſt the <hi>acidum</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from <hi>Fire,</hi> (which they do by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſometimes expoſing to the <hi>air,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37259:9"/>with the addition of ſomewhat which dints the foreſaid <hi>Acidum</hi>) may then by Art, be made to ſplit into <hi>Oyle</hi> and <hi>urinous Spirit,</hi> or <hi>volatile Salt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to that great objection againſt the <hi>acidity</hi> of <hi>fixt lixivial Alcalies,</hi> viz. the precipitation of ſuch ſolutions made with <hi>Alcalies</hi> by <hi>Acids,</hi> inaſmuch as it is generally obſerv'd, that what ſolutions <hi>Alcalies</hi> make, are moſt promptly <hi>precipitated</hi> by <hi>Acids.</hi> I anſwer, Firſt, That although what more ſimple, I mean, <hi>volatile Alcalies</hi> do diſſolve, are precipitated very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily by <hi>Acids, &amp; vice verſa,</hi> yet where <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies</hi> are more complicated, and interwoven with other eſſential parts, there the <hi>precipitation</hi> by <hi>Acids,</hi> of what thoſe already have diſſolv'd, are in no wiſe wholly aſcribable to them as <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies,</hi> but equally compitible to other parts in the concretion.</p>
            <p>And in the next place I anſwer, that even ſome <hi>acids</hi> are capable of <hi>precipitating</hi> what others have <hi>diſſolv'd;</hi> to prove and illuſtrate which, I try'd this following inſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> I took a clear ſolution of <hi>ſaccharum Saturni,</hi> which I had prepared with <hi>distilled Vinegar,</hi> which no man will deny to be an <hi>Acid;</hi> upon which I poured a pretty ſmart <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> whereupon it preſently became <hi>Milkie,</hi> and caus'd a <hi>precipitation</hi> of a pure <hi>white calx</hi> of <hi>Saturn,</hi> which <hi>precipitation</hi> may alſo be done with <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Salt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37259:9"/>
            <p>The ſame likewiſe will <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Salt</hi> do, poured upon a ſolution of <hi>refin'd Silver,</hi> made in double its weight of <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that admirable anomolous neutral concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, call'd <hi>Luna Cornea,</hi> mentioned by the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Boyle</hi> in his <hi>origin</hi> of <hi>forms:</hi> and not onely <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Salt</hi> but alſo <hi>Oyle</hi> of <hi>Vitriol</hi> will cauſe the like <hi>precipitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence its obvious to any eye, that what ſome <hi>Acids</hi> diſſolve, others may precipitate from the <hi>congenealneſs</hi> of the <hi>ſolvend,</hi> to one <hi>ſolvend</hi> more then another: For both thoſe wherein the <hi>ſolutions</hi> of the <hi>metals</hi> were made, viz. <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Vinegar</hi> and <hi>Aqua-fortis,</hi> are as undoubtedly <hi>acids,</hi> as thoſe which cauſe the <hi>precipitations,</hi> viz. <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Salt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the precipitation of bodies depend not upon <hi>acid</hi> or <hi>alcalizate Liquors,</hi> as ſuch; but upon the <hi>conſanguinity</hi> (if I may ſo ſay) of <hi>bodies</hi> or <hi>ſolvends,</hi> to <hi>liquors</hi> or <hi>ſolvents, viz.</hi> whilſt an <hi>acid</hi> having diſſolv'd one <hi>body,</hi> meeting with another <hi>akin</hi> thereto, lets the former <hi>fall,</hi> and from an abſtruce <hi>affinity</hi> of parts, <hi>diſsolves</hi> the latter.</p>
            <p>From whence it need not ſeem <hi>heterodox,</hi> (although to the moſt it may, as yet, a <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox</hi>) to ſay, that <hi>fixt Alcalies</hi> open the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>mineral Sulphurs,</hi> as they are <hi>acido-Sulphurous Salts;</hi> and that chiefly as they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37259:10"/>of the <hi>acidum</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> aſſum'd by <hi>calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:</hi> and that <hi>precipitations</hi> of the ſame <hi>ſolutions</hi> may be perform'd (and that too without the leaſt abſurdity in <hi>Philoſophy</hi>) by other ſupervening <hi>Acids,</hi> as we have even now demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>As I obſerv'd all <hi>fixt Alcalies</hi> made out of <hi>Vegetables,</hi> to work upon <hi>Mineral Sulphurs,</hi> on the account of their being <hi>Acido-Sulphurous-Salts;</hi> ſo I could not otherwiſe (whilſt I look'd upon the matter with a very intent eye) judge of <hi>calx vive;</hi> whoſe manner of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in opening the bodies of <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> and other <hi>Mineral Sulphurs,</hi> I could not charge to any other then its <hi>Acid,</hi> which it had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the <hi>Fire,</hi> in the very <hi>calcination</hi> of that ſort of Stone, call'd <hi>Lapis calcarius,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Free-ſtone or Lime-ſtone) which that it chiefly partakes of the <hi>Acidum</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> and thereby performs not only that, but various other effects, we have already in ſhort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, and ſhall further in <hi>Lithologia Phyſica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the premiſſes it will eaſily appear, in <hi>confirmation</hi> of our <hi>former Doctrine,</hi> that all ſolutions of <hi>Mineral Sulphurs</hi> in the bowels of the <hi>Earth,</hi> are made by their <hi>peculiar Acids;</hi> and that other ſolutions made by <hi>Art,</hi> are but from the ſame <hi>principles</hi> under other <hi>diſguiſes;</hi> Therefore that which opens the body of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37259:10"/>in theſe <hi>Mineral Marcaſites,</hi> through which this <hi>water</hi> (we treat of) <hi>runs,</hi> muſt of neceſſity be an <hi>Acidum,</hi> which afterwards is precipitated by another <hi>Acid</hi> of the <hi>Alom-bed,</hi> through which at laſt it paſſeth.</p>
            <p>As to that <hi>experiment</hi> we gave to <hi>illuſtrate</hi> the cauſe and manner of making that <hi>water,</hi> by opening thoſe <hi>vitriolin Marcaſites</hi> with <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime,</hi> in our <hi>Hydrological Eſſays,</hi> although we there imputed it to the <hi>alcali;</hi> yet now from ſecond and more mature thoughts, grounded upon experiment, as aforeſaid, find it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; where we profeſs ſuch an avowed <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyteſhip</hi> to truth (ſufficiently amiable and worthy in it ſelf) as upon nearer apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof, grounded upon better <hi>weighed principles,</hi> to decline what we have formerly at greater diſtance in any matter opiniated, and in this particular, have thence reaſon to wave the former, and to aſcribe the ſolution of this great <hi>Phoenomenon</hi> to the latter, <hi>viz.</hi> to the <hi>Acid</hi> in <hi>calx vive,</hi> which, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, bears an <hi>analogy</hi> with that <hi>Acidum,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uſeth by her own <hi>Chymistry,</hi> in the <hi>intrails</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> for the ſolutions and extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Sulphurs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>5th</hi> thing propoſed to <hi>diſcourſe</hi> of in this our <hi>method, viz.</hi> how this <hi>water</hi> comes not much ſhort, as to its <hi>original principles,</hi> nor is much inferiour in its efficacy, to ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37259:11"/>other <hi>Sulphurcus waters,</hi> which are <hi>Hot-Baths,</hi> which is evident (beſides what has already been ſaid) by the ſequel thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the manner of uſe of both, in reſpect of what they have been, are now reciprocal; thoſe of <hi>Hot-Baths</hi> being formerly chiefly known for <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> and theſe for <hi>inward uſe.</hi> But now of late are found, the former in ſome caſes to be ſucceſsful for inward uſe; the latter by <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> are now eminently remarkable for <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward application:</hi> ſo that the manner of uſe of them <hi>per ſe</hi> conſidered, is inverted, and in a mutual reſpect, is reciprocal.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>virtues</hi> of thoſe <hi>Hot-Baths</hi> (which are lately found remarkable for inward as well as outward uſe) I mean eſpecially thoſe of our <hi>own Country,</hi> the Reader may conſult Dr. <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> his <hi>diſcourſe</hi> of <hi>Natural Baths,</hi> and of late the <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> who have and yet do attend thoſe <hi>waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>virtues</hi> of this <hi>Sulphur-water</hi> (our preſent Theme) as to the uſe thereof as an inward <hi>Medicine,</hi> the Reader may conſult Dr. <hi>French</hi> his Book, and the patient the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> there. It remains now to ſpeak of it in <hi>relation</hi> to outward uſe, as a <hi>Bath,</hi> and this leads me to the next conſiderable, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That <hi>artificial heating</hi> of the <hi>water,</hi> bears ſome <hi>analogy</hi> to the <hi>inbred heat</hi> of thoſe other <hi>Baths,</hi> as they come <hi>hot</hi> out of the <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37259:11"/>
            <p>To the illuſtrating of which we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>Sulphur</hi> or <hi>Brimſtone</hi> (according to out former Doctrine, that it may become <hi>ſolvable</hi> in <hi>water,</hi> is either to be <hi>comminuted</hi> and <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiz'd</hi> by the native or ſuperinduc'd <hi>Acids,</hi> and that by a brisk <hi>Fermentation</hi> from the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>colliſions</hi> of the two <hi>principles,</hi> whence the heat of <hi>natural Baths,</hi> as aforeſaid, or elſe the <hi>Sulphur,</hi> by ſleighter <hi>touches,</hi> and ſlenderer <hi>vibrations</hi> from congenial <hi>Acids,</hi> becomes ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in a <hi>preterlabent water,</hi> whoſe <hi>heat</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (if any) in the ſource of <hi>Fermentation,</hi> is but gentle: yet by that ſleight ſolution of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> it becomes capable of precipitation by another <hi>Acid,</hi> (viz. of <hi>Alom</hi>) as happens in this <hi>water</hi> we treat of: That a body of <hi>Brimſtone</hi> is precipitated is evident from Dr. <hi>Neals obſervation,</hi> concerning a cruſt of <hi>Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone</hi> which he found under the <hi>Stones</hi> of the <hi>Old-Well</hi> at the removing them, through whoſe crevices the <hi>water ſprang:</hi> and that the <hi>Aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity</hi> by which the precipitation is made, is from the <hi>Alom,</hi> doth as clearly appear from the <hi>Aluminous black Stones,</hi> found in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther digging for a better <hi>Spring.</hi> Now what remains in the water after the foreſaid <hi>precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> is no other then the <hi>apporrhea,</hi> or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>affluvium</hi> of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> which being diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the whole body of the <hi>water,</hi> is always upon the wing, flying off continually.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37259:12"/>
            <p>This <hi>effluvium</hi> of <hi>Sulphur</hi> complicated with <hi>Salt</hi> in the body of the <hi>water,</hi> although it be very <hi>volatile,</hi> (as I ſaid) yet that it may the better <hi>permeate</hi> our bodies, in order to the performing thoſe expected helps, its neceſſary (as to outward uſe) that the <hi>waters</hi> ſhould be <hi>heated,</hi> by which the <hi>volatile parts</hi> are put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a more <hi>vigorous motion,</hi> and made capable of <hi>penetrating</hi> our <hi>juices</hi> the better: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>in frigido,</hi> the Sulphurous parts are by a volatility continually winding off, yet by <hi>heating,</hi> its put into a more lively <hi>action,</hi> and made more readily <hi>Fermentable</hi> with the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of our bodies.</p>
            <p>Now that the <hi>Sulphur</hi> in this <hi>water</hi> conſiſts of tenuous parts, and very <hi>volatile,</hi> is evident (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what already has been ſaid) by this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>obſervation,</hi> viz. that during the time I <hi>Bath'd</hi> therein, and afterwards went to Bed, having laid my <hi>Silver-ſtudded Watch</hi> upon the Table, thereby to obſerve the time of <hi>Bathing</hi> and <hi>Sweating,</hi> I found the <hi>ſteam</hi> of the <hi>heated water</hi> had guilded it at ſuch a diſtance; and is ſo <hi>conſpicuous,</hi> as to change the colour, (as I have obſerv'd) of the <hi>Braſs-Candlesticks</hi> which ſtood in the next room to the <hi>Bath.</hi> Yea, although this be very <hi>volatile,</hi> yet that it doth not ſudd enly take <hi>wing,</hi> is hence evident, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe after three hours time, that the <hi>water</hi> had been heated, when I got up, I dipt a <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37259:12"/>therein, which it ſtill guilded very readily.</p>
            <p n="7">7. As to the <hi>artificial</hi> reſemblance of <hi>Sulphur Baths</hi> by imitation of <hi>Nature:</hi> Firſt as to <hi>Hot-Baths,</hi> that indeed we fall ſhort in, becauſe its the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> in the great <hi>Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Mineral juices,</hi> in order to the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Mineral concretes:</hi> And ſeeing <hi>Art</hi> doth of neceſſity always <hi>petere principia</hi> from <hi>Nature,</hi> and that thoſe <hi>principles</hi> are <hi>ſeminal,</hi> therefore not to be imitated by <hi>Art;</hi> But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as all <hi>Fermentation</hi> amongſt <hi>Minerals,</hi> (as we have formerly ſhew'd) conſiſts in the <hi>inward conflicts</hi> of <hi>Mineral Acids</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> and that according to the different aſſaults of the ſaid <hi>Acids,</hi> upon varieties of <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend the <hi>ſpecification</hi> or formal difference of <hi>Mineral Waters;</hi> ſo in particular this <hi>Water</hi> being chiefly compos'd of a <hi>Sulphur,</hi> wrought upon by an <hi>Acid,</hi> and afterwards precipitated by another; the reſemblance by <hi>Art</hi> muſt be from the ſame ſort of <hi>principles,</hi> grounded upon the natural: Thus what an <hi>Acid,</hi> (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or ſuperinduc'd) performs upon <hi>Mineral Sulphur,</hi> in order to the making that <hi>Mineral Solution,</hi> required for the <hi>natural compoſure</hi> of this <hi>Water;</hi> The ſame will the <hi>Acidum</hi> of <hi>calx vive,</hi> or of <hi>fixt Alcalies</hi> do <hi>ſuo modo</hi> to <hi>Common Brimſtone,</hi> or other <hi>Mineral Sulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Concretions,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37259:13"/>
            <p>And laſtly, As to the virtues hereof: This <hi>Water</hi> being gradually <hi>heated</hi> (as is ſaid) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a <hi>Bath,</hi> whoſe <hi>Sulphur</hi> hereby firſt <hi>pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates</hi> the better into our <hi>Fermental juices,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing them, if <hi>languid</hi> through <hi>Hydropick Acids,</hi> or ſpurious, through <hi>Scorbutick Acids,</hi> in the one by helping (with other concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Medicaments) to remove obſtructions from <hi>coagulated Acids;</hi> in the other, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dipitating, altering and ſweetening <hi>Scorbutick Acids,</hi> the cauſe of pains and particular tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereby it the better reacheth to dint that <hi>Fermental Acor</hi> of the <hi>Gout,</hi> impreſs'd upon the <hi>Synovia</hi> of the <hi>Joints,</hi> ſo eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to the <hi>adjacent Nerves;</hi> hence is the reaſon why its found ſo effectual for the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey, Gout,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe theſe forenamed Diſeaſes are chiefly determined and ſpecifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Acids,</hi> coagulated upon different hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and parts: For its the Eſſential efficacy (if I may ſo ſay) of a <hi>ſubtiliz'd Sulphur</hi> to dint <hi>Acids,</hi> and thereby to reſolve ſuch as are coagulated; ſo that to me the <hi>diſcuſſion</hi> of all <hi>tumours,</hi> whether <hi>Scorbutick</hi> or others, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the <hi>reſolving</hi> thoſe coagulated <hi>Acids,</hi> the intimate and real efficients thereof. No ſooner doth a Spurious predominant <hi>Acid</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulate any portion of the <hi>blood,</hi> or other <hi>juice</hi> in any part of the body, but preſently
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37259:13"/>an obſtruction of thoſe parts happen, more or leſs, according to the intenſe or remiſs degree of the prevalent <hi>Acid,</hi> which as it falls out in Veſſels or Bowels reputed more or leſs noble, <hi>viz.</hi> intenſely or remiſsly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>fabrick</hi> and <hi>circulation</hi> of <hi>vital juices,</hi> and <hi>animal Spirits,</hi> ſo it becomes the patron of different ſorts of Diſeaſes; ſome whereof eaſily bending to more facile <hi>methods</hi> of <hi>Cure;</hi> others more ſtubborn (of which are the laſt mentioned) not yielding but to more vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, ſubtiliz'd, and penetrative <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> ſuch as are in this and other <hi>Sulphurous Baths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which (I mean our <hi>Sulphur-Bath</hi>) <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick</hi> and <hi>Podagrick</hi> Patients have received conſiderable relief: for which cauſe, many perſons, finding thereby ſo much alleviation of the otherwiſe grievous Symptoms, and ſuch a mittigation of the ſeverity of future fits of the <hi>Gout,</hi> (I mean as to what they might have expected, without ſuch a previous help) do voluntarily make their <hi>annual returns</hi> to the <hi>Bath:</hi> of which I could give ſeveral inſtances, but that it doth not ſuit my preſent deſign.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the uſe of this <hi>Bath,</hi> the blood and humours are <hi>purified,</hi> whence it becomes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for <hi>Blotches, Scabs, Itches, Elephantiaſis.</hi> or <hi>Baſtard Leproſie,</hi> and other <hi>Scorbutick impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi> of the <hi>Blood;</hi> For it procures moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Sweats,</hi> whereby the other impure
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37259:14"/>
               <hi>Acids,</hi> (which are precipitated or caſt off from the <hi>Blood</hi> in its <hi>circulation,</hi> and topically <hi>fixed</hi> upon this or the other <hi>external part</hi>) are looſened, diſſolv'd, or mortifi'd; which deprav'd <hi>Acids</hi> lodge in the habit of the body, having their very <hi>Roots fixed</hi> in the ultimate digeſtion, vitiating the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Latex,</hi> ſent thither for the ordinary nutriment of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in the common circulation thereof; yea, they are ſometimes ſo <hi>fixed</hi> upon their own <hi>Roots,</hi> as to tranſmute the otherwiſe <hi>alimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary juice,</hi> by their <hi>Ferments,</hi> into thoſe <hi>exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal impurities:</hi> which they do as really as a <hi>Crab-tree-ſcions,</hi> or <hi>Bud,</hi> ingraffed into a good <hi>Apple-ſtock,</hi> doth (from its own <hi>ſeminal Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) turn the <hi>juice</hi> of the <hi>Stock,</hi> into the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>property</hi> of a <hi>Crab:</hi> So that in ſuch <hi>external vitiating</hi> of the <hi>humours,</hi> which are onely skin deep, the applications in order to <hi>Cure</hi> or <hi>Abſtorſion,</hi> muſt be ſuch as can morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, diſſolve, alter or correct the foreſaid <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally ſcituated Acids,</hi> which may be, and is, moſt aptly perform'd by this <hi>Sulphur-Bath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that in many the like caſes, where thoſe <hi>Acids</hi> are moſt <hi>pertinacious,</hi> and the <hi>Maladies</hi> thence have taken <hi>deepest root,</hi> viz. in the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantaſis, Pſora, Leproſie,</hi> &amp;c. the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and uſual <hi>Purges</hi> and <hi>Diaphoreticks,</hi> are altogether <hi>inſignificant,</hi> becauſe they reach not thoſe deeply impreſs'd <hi>Acids,</hi> nor correct
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37259:14"/>thoſe <hi>ſpurious Ferments,</hi> ſeated, yea rooted in the <hi>habit</hi> of the <hi>body;</hi> which ſuch <hi>ſubtiliz'd Sulphurs,</hi> as are in this <hi>Bath</hi> skilfully applyed (with other aſſiſting Medicines) are apt chiefly to perform.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which <hi>external impurities,</hi> the <hi>Lues Venerea</hi> (being made by carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract) may not improperly be reckoned; which conſiſts in a peculiar ſort (in its kind) of a contagious <hi>Fermental Acid,</hi> thence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to the <hi>juices</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> eſpecially where the <hi>contagious Ferment,</hi> by the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, entered; which by its <hi>corroding acor,</hi> as a cauſtick, fretting and inflaming thoſe <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der parts,</hi> or <hi>coagulating</hi> the <hi>juices</hi> of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts (brought thither by an afflux of humours) into <hi>venereal tumours,</hi> whoſe reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Ferments</hi> yet lodge in their Bellies, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in both become the <hi>Authors</hi> of <hi>Noctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pains, polutions,</hi> &amp;c. to the dinting of which ſpurious <hi>Fermental acor,</hi> (the cauſe of the aforeſaid dolours) the juſt mulct of that Sin muſt be chiefly aim'd at, in the curing thereof: which beſides other <hi>Diaphoreticks,</hi> may very well be perform'd by the help of this <hi>Bath:</hi> And that too, becauſe <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> (eſpecially ſuch as are <hi>prepared</hi> and <hi>volatiz'd</hi> by the <hi>admirable Chymistry</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> in the body or bowels of the Earth) do <hi>ſweeten</hi> and <hi>morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> all ſuch ſort of <hi>Acids:</hi> For which purpoſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37259:15"/>in order to the Cure thereof, not only <hi>Bathing,</hi> (and ſome other aſſiſting <hi>Diaphoreticks</hi>) but alſo the <hi>drinking</hi> the ſame <hi>water</hi> is requiſite.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the uſe of this <hi>Bath,</hi> the <hi>nervous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies</hi> are alſo much helped, of which ſort are <hi>Cramps, Convulſions, Palſies, Apoplexies,</hi> being cauſed from the various ſeiſures upon theſe <hi>juices,</hi> alſo from the <hi>contorſions</hi> and <hi>diſable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the Veſſels or <hi>Conduit-pipes,</hi> (the <hi>Nerves</hi>) thoſe <hi>juices</hi> are circulated, or at leaſt carryed in, being the <hi>Organs</hi> wherein the <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits</hi> move in order to ſenſe, motion, and other <hi>vital ſunctions,</hi> proper thereto, whoſe tone are altered, contorted, contracted, or relax'd by ſeveral ſorts of ſupervening <hi>Acids,</hi> ſent up in <hi>flatulent ſteams,</hi> reſulting from ſome ſpurious ſubordinate <hi>Fermentation,</hi> whoſe <hi>Acids</hi> being ſtrong, have prevail'd, and by a ſort of <hi>ſublimation</hi> are at length <hi>fixt</hi> upon thoſe <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cords,</hi> cauſing obſtructions, contractions, relaxations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (according to the <hi>morbid Acids</hi>) the cauſes of Diſeaſes relating to the <hi>genus nervoſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as <hi>Acids</hi> are the cauſe why <hi>Nerves</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo thoſe various <hi>alterations</hi> in their <hi>tone</hi> or <hi>texture,</hi> by contractions, relaxations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in their <hi>juices</hi> by coagulations, and thence obſtructions, or other debilitudes, whereby the volatile nimble <hi>animal Spirits</hi> become <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted</hi> in their <hi>motion,</hi> being block'd up by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37259:15"/>ſuch ſort of <hi>coagulations:</hi> ſo in order to the Cure of theſe Diſeaſes, ſuch <hi>Medicaments</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> are to be inquired into, as may <hi>dint, alter,</hi> and <hi>dulcifie</hi> ſuch kinds of <hi>Acids,</hi> and thence may looſen the <hi>contracted,</hi> ſmooth and make even the <hi>contorted,</hi> may ſtrengthen the <hi>relaxed Cords,</hi> yea and may every way anſwer the <hi>indications</hi> of the deprav'd <hi>tones</hi> of thoſe <hi>animal pendula's</hi> or <hi>vital ſtrings,</hi> whereby the impriſoned <hi>Spirits,</hi> (the immediate product of <hi>vital Fermentation</hi> may again be ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and all the <hi>animal functions</hi> be reſtored to their <hi>pristine ſtate:</hi> of which ſort are our <hi>Sulphur-Bath,</hi> which by correcting the <hi>Acids,</hi> ſupple and ſoften the <hi>contracted,</hi> ſtrengthen and bind up the <hi>weak,</hi> and very much repair, in the <hi>maine,</hi> the <hi>deprav'd tone</hi> of the <hi>genus Nervoſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, By the uſe of this <hi>Bath,</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the tendons, and muſculous parts, I mean <hi>ſtiffneſs</hi> of the <hi>Limbs, Joynts,</hi> &amp;c. (where the contraction is not too fixed) are often remedied: For theſe outward maladies being cauſed through ſome rejected <hi>Acids,</hi> which wanting a due <hi>Fermentative motion</hi> to give them <hi>wing</hi> by <hi>perſpiration,</hi> are <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulated</hi> or <hi>hardened</hi> (partly by the aſſiſtance of the Air) in the external parts; but by the <hi>Sulphur</hi> in the <hi>Bath,</hi> the pores being open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they diſſolv'd, and put into <hi>motion,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37259:16"/>are either ſweetened or carryed off.</p>
            <p>Alſo its proper for alleviating <hi>Aches, Old pains, Strains, Sciatica's,</hi> (which is a ſort of <hi>Gout</hi> in thoſe parts) <hi>Rheumatiſms,</hi> and other griefs now too tedious to relate: concerning moſt of which we might have given ſom par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtances, but that it doth not ſuit with our preſent deſign, undertaking chiefly a <hi>rational account</hi> of its <hi>cauſes,</hi> and in general of its <hi>virtues:</hi> As to the particular caſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which may confirm what we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready depoſited, as to the medicinal efficacy thereof, we ſhall refer to another oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:37259:16"/>
            <head>Certain Books Printed, and to be Sold at the <hi>Pellican</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> London.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>SPencers</hi> view of the State of <hi>Ireland,</hi> fol.</item>
               <item>Dyſtica Regum Angliae, —</item>
               <item>Seberi Index in Homerum, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Waraeus de Scriptoribus Hiberniae, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Strada's</hi> Muſical Duel between Natural and Artificial Muſick, or the Nightingal and Harper, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſerius</hi> de Primordijs Eccleſiarum Britanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— Ejuſd. Hiſtoria Gotteſchalci de Praedeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— Ejuſd. Sylloge veterum Epiſtolarum Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernicarum. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Seldeni de Synedrijs liber 1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ferrarij Euclides Phyſicus, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chryſoſtomi Democritus Reviviſcens de Vita &amp; Philoſophia Democrati &amp; de Manna Liber, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sancta-clara Deus Natura &amp; Gratia, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Frommenij Metaphyſica. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Jonſtoni Lexici Chymici liber 2. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:37259:17"/>
               <item>French Grammar, by the Doctors of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> for Reformation of the French Tongue, In French and Engliſh, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secrets Reveal'd, or an open Entrance to the Shut-Pallace of the King, containing the chief Treaſury of Chymiſtry, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Philoſophical Epitaph, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> together with a Catalogue of Chymical Books in three Parts, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Simpſons</hi> Philoſophical Diſcourſe of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation; with a Diſcourſe of the <hi>Sulphur-Bath</hi> at <hi>Knarsbrough</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Caveat</hi> for the <hi>Proteſtant Clergy,</hi> or a true account of the Sufferings of the <hi>Engliſh Clergy</hi> upon the Reſtitution of Popery in the days of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paracelſus</hi> his <hi>Archidoxes,</hi> diſcovering the way of making <hi>Quinteſsences, Arcanums, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, Elixirs,</hi> &amp;c. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His <hi>Aurora</hi> and Treaſure of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, together with the Water-ſtone of of the Wiſe-men, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fame and Confeſſion of the Fraternity of the <hi>Roſie-Croſs,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Where likewiſe moſt ſorts of Chymical or Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Books, may be had, whether in Engliſh or Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37259:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
